<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="mapping-chapter">
  <title>Mapping</title>

  <para>Rich mapping support is provided by the
  <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname>.
  <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname> has a rich metadata model that
  provides a full feature set of functionality to map domain objects to
  MongoDB documents.The mapping metadata model is populated using annotations
  on your domain objects. However, the infrastructure is not limited to using
  annotations as the only source of metadata information. The
  <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname> also allows you to map objects
  to documents without providing any additional metadata, by following a set
  of conventions.</para>

  <para>In this section we will describe the features of the
  MongoMappingConverter. How to use conventions for mapping objects to
  documents and how to override those conventions with annotation based
  mapping metadata.</para>

  <note>
    <para><classname>SimpleMongoConverter</classname> has been deprecated in
    Spring Data MongoDB M3 as all of its functionality has been subsumed into
    <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname>.</para>
  </note>

  <section id="mapping-conventions">
    <title>Convention based Mapping</title>

    <para><classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname> has a few conventions
    for mapping objects to documents when no additional mapping metadata is
    provided. The conventions are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The short Java class name is mapped to the collection name in
        the following manner. The class
        '<classname>com.bigbank.SavingsAccount</classname>' maps to
        '<literal>savingsAccount</literal>' collection name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All nested objects are stored as nested objects in the document
        and *not* as DBRefs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The converter will use any Spring Converters registered with it
        to override the default mapping of object properties to document
        field/values.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The fields of an object are used to convert to and from fields
        in the document. Public JavaBean properties are not used.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can have a single non-zero argument constructor whose
        constructor argument names match top level field names of document,
        that constructor will be used. Otherwise the zero arg constructor will
        be used. if there is more than one non-zero argument constructor an
        exception will be thrown.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="mapping.conventions.id-field">
      <title>How the '_id' field is handled in the mapping layer</title>

      <para>MongoDB requires that you have an '_id' field for all documents.
      If you don't provide one the driver will assign a ObjectId with a
      generated value. The "_id" field can be of any type the, other than
      arrays, so long as it is unique. The driver naturally supports all
      primitive types and Dates. When using the
      <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname> there are certain rules
      that govern how properties from the Java class is mapped to this '_id'
      field.</para>

      <para>The following outlines what field will be mapped to the '_id'
      document field:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A field annotated with <classname>@Id</classname>
            (<classname>org.springframework.data.annotation.Id</classname>)
            will be mapped to the '_id' field.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A field without an annotation but named
            <classname>id</classname> will be mapped to the '_id'
            field.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>The following outlines what type conversion, if any, will be done
      on the property mapped to the _id document field.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a field named 'id' is declared as a String or BigInteger in
          the Java class it will be converted to and stored as an ObjectId if
          possible. ObjectId as a field type is also valid. If you specify a
          value for 'id' in your application, the conversion to an ObjectId is
          detected to the MongoDBdriver. If the specified 'id' value cannot be
          converted to an ObjectId, then the value will be stored as is in the
          document's _id field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a field named ' id' id field is not declared as a String,
          BigInteger, or ObjectID in the Java class then you should assign it
          a value in your application so it can be stored 'as-is' in the
          document's _id field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If no field named 'id' is present in the Java class then an
          implicit '_id' file will be generated by the driver but not mapped
          to a property or field of the Java class.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>When querying and updating <classname>MongoTemplate</classname>
      will use the converter to handle conversions of the
      <classname>Query</classname> and <classname>Update</classname> objects
      that correspond to the above rules for saving documents so field names
      and types used in your queries will be able to match what is in your
      domain classes.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="mapping-configuration">
    <title>Mapping Configuration</title>

    <para>Unless explicitly configured, an instance of
    <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname> is created by default when
    creating a <classname>MongoTemplate</classname>. You can create your own
    instance of the <classname>MappingMongoConverter</classname> so as to tell
    it where to scan the classpath at startup your domain classes in order to
    extract metadata and construct indexes. Also, by creating your own
    instance you can register Spring converters to use for mapping specific
    classes to and from the database.</para>

    <para>You can configure the <classname>MongoMappingConverter</classname>
    as well as <classname>com.mongodb.Mongo</classname> and MongoTemplate
    either using Java or XML based metadata. Here is an example using Spring's
    Java based configuration</para>

    <example>
      <title>@Configuration class to configure MongoDB mapping support</title>

      <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public class GeoSpatialAppConfig extends AbstractMongoConfiguration {

  @Bean
  public Mongo mongo() throws Exception {
    return new Mongo("localhost");
  }

  @Override
  public String getDatabaseName() {
    return "database";
  }

  @Override
  public String getMappingBasePackage() {
    return "com.bigbank.domain";
  }

  // the following are optional


  @Bean
  @Override
  public CustomConversions customConversions() throws Exception {
    List&lt;Converter&lt;?, ?&gt;&gt; converterList = new ArrayList&lt;Converter&lt;?, ?&gt;&gt;();
    converterList.add(new org.springframework.data.mongodb.test.PersonReadConverter());
    converterList.add(new org.springframework.data.mongodb.test.PersonWriteConverter());
    return new CustomConversions(converterList);
  }

  @Bean
  public LoggingEventListener&lt;MongoMappingEvent&gt; mappingEventsListener() {
    return new LoggingEventListener&lt;MongoMappingEvent&gt;();
  }

}</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para><classname>AbstractMongoConfiguration</classname> requires you to
    implement methods that define a <classname>com.mongodb.Mongo</classname>
    as well as provide a database name.
    <classname>AbstractMongoConfiguration</classname> also has a method you
    can override named '<methodname>getMappingBasePackage</methodname>' which
    tells the converter where to scan for classes annotated with the
    <classname>@org.springframework.data.mongodb.core.mapping.Document</classname>
    annotation.</para>

    <para>You can add additional converters to the converter by overriding the
    method afterMappingMongoConverterCreation. Also shown in the above example
    is a <classname>LoggingEventListener</classname> which logs
    <classname>MongoMappingEvent</classname>s that are posted onto Spring's
    <interfacename>ApplicationContextEvent</interfacename>
    infrastructure.</para>

    <note>
      <para>AbstractMongoConfiguration will create a MongoTemplate instance
      and registered with the container under the name 'mongoTemplate'.</para>
    </note>

    <para>You can also override the method <literal>UserCredentials
    getUserCredentials()</literal> to provide the username and password
    information to connect to the database.</para>

    <para>Spring's MongoDB namespace enables you to easily enable mapping
    functionality in XML</para>

    <example>
      <title>XML schema to configure MongoDB mapping support</title>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
       xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
       xmlns:context="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context"
       xmlns:mongo="http://www.springframework.org/schema/data/mongo"
       xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context http://www.springframework.org/schema/context/spring-context-3.0.xsd
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/data/mongo http://www.springframework.org/schema/data/mongo/spring-mongo-1.0.xsd
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd"&gt;

  &lt;!-- Default bean name is 'mongo' --&gt;
  &lt;mongo:mongo host="localhost" port="27017"/&gt;

  &lt;mongo:db-factory dbname="database" mongo-ref="mongo"/&gt;

  &lt;!-- by default look for a Mongo object named 'mongo' - default name used for the converter is 'mappingConverter' --&gt;
  &lt;mongo:mapping-converter base-package="com.bigbank.domain"&gt;
    &lt;mongo:custom-converters&gt;
      &lt;mongo:converter ref="readConverter"/&gt;
      &lt;mongo:converter&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.data.mongodb.test.PersonWriteConverter"/&gt;
      &lt;/mongo:converter&gt;
    &lt;/mongo:custom-converters&gt;
  &lt;/mongo:mapping-converter&gt;

  &lt;bean id="readConverter" class="org.springframework.data.mongodb.test.PersonReadConverter"/&gt;

  &lt;!-- set the mapping converter to be used by the MongoTemplate --&gt;
  &lt;bean id="mongoTemplate" class="org.springframework.data.mongodb.core.MongoTemplate"&gt;
    &lt;constructor-arg name="mongoDbFactory" ref="mongoDbFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;constructor-arg name="mongoConverter" ref="mappingConverter"/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;bean class="org.springframework.data.mongodb.core.mapping.event.LoggingEventListener"/&gt;

&lt;/beans
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>The <code>base-package</code> property tells it where to scan for
    classes annotated with the
    <classname>@org.springframework.data.mongodb.core.mapping.Document</classname>
    annotation.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="mapping-usage">
    <title>Metadata based Mapping</title>

    <para>To take full advantage of the object mapping functionality inside
    the Spring Data/MongoDB support, you should annotate your mapped objects
    with the
    <classname>@org.springframework.data.mongodb.core.mapping.Document</classname>
    annotation. Although it is not necessary for the mapping framework to have
    this annotation (your POJOs will be mapped correctly, even without any
    annotations), it allows the classpath scanner to find and pre-process your
    domain objects to extract the necessary metadata. If you don't use this
    annotation, your application will take a slight performance hit the first
    time you store a domain object because the mapping framework needs to
    build up its internal metadata model so it knows about the properties of
    your domain object and how to persist them.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Example domain object</title>

      <programlisting language="java">package com.mycompany.domain;

@Document
public class Person {

  @Id
  private ObjectId id;

  @Indexed
  private Integer ssn;

  private String firstName;

  @Indexed
  private String lastName;

}
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <important>
      <para>The <classname>@Id</classname> annotation tells the mapper which
      property you want to use for the MongoDB <code>_id</code> property and
      the <classname>@Indexed</classname> annotation tells the mapping
      framework to call <code>ensureIndex</code> on that property of your
      document, making searches faster.</para>
    </important>

    <important>
      <para>Automatic index creation is only done for types annotated with
      <classname>@Document</classname>.</para>
    </important>

    <section id="mapping-usage-annotations">
      <title>Mapping annotation overview</title>

      <para>The MappingMongoConverter can use metadata to drive the mapping of
      objects to documents. An overview of the annotations is provided
      below</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Id </literal>- applied at the field level to mark
          the field used for identiy purpose.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Document</literal> - applied at the class level to
          indicate this class is a candidate for mapping to the database. You
          can specify the name of the collection where the database will be
          stored.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@DBRef</literal> - applied at the field to indicate
          it is to be stored using a com.mongodb.DBRef.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Indexed</literal> - applied at the field level to
          describe how to index the field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@CompoundIndex</literal> - applied at the type level
          to declare Compound Indexes</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@GeoSpatialIndexed</literal> - applied at the field
          level to describe how to geoindex the field.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@TextIndexed</literal> - applied at the field level
          to mark the field to be included in the text index.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Language</literal> - applied at the field level to
          set the language override property for text index.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Transient</literal> - by default all private fields
          are mapped to the document, this annotation excludes the field where
          it is applied from being stored in the database</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@PersistenceConstructor</literal> - marks a given
          constructor - even a package protected one - to use when
          instantiating the object from the database. Constructor arguments
          are mapped by name to the key values in the retrieved
          DBObject.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Value</literal> - this annotation is part of the
          Spring Framework . Within the mapping framework it can be applied to
          constructor arguments. This lets you use a Spring Expression
          Language statement to transform a key's value retrieved in the
          database before it is used to construct a domain object. In order to
          reference a property of a given document one has to use expressions
          like: <code>@Value("#root.myProperty")</code> where
          <literal>root</literal> refers to the root of the given
          document.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>@Field</literal> - applied at the field level and
          described the name of the field as it will be represented in the
          MongoDB BSON document thus allowing the name to be different than
          the fieldname of the class.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The mapping metadata infrastructure is defined in a seperate
      spring-data-commons project that is technology agnostic. Specific
      subclasses are using in the MongoDB support to support annotation based
      metadata. Other strategies are also possible to put in place if there is
      demand.</para>

      <para>Here is an example of a more complex mapping.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">@Document
@CompoundIndexes({
    @CompoundIndex(name = "age_idx", def = "{'lastName': 1, 'age': -1}")
})
public class Person&lt;T extends Address&gt; {

  @Id
  private String id;

  @Indexed(unique = true)
  private Integer ssn;

  @Field("fName")
  private String firstName;

  @Indexed
  private String lastName;

  private Integer age;

  @Transient
  private Integer accountTotal;

  @DBRef
  private List&lt;Account&gt; accounts;

  private T address;

  
  public Person(Integer ssn) {
    this.ssn = ssn;
  }
  
  @PersistenceConstructor
  public Person(Integer ssn, String firstName, String lastName, Integer age, T address) {
    this.ssn = ssn;
    this.firstName = firstName;
    this.lastName = lastName;
    this.age = age;
    this.address = address;
  }

  public String getId() {
    return id;
  }

 // no setter for Id.  (getter is only exposed for some unit testing)

  public Integer getSsn() {
    return ssn;
  }


// other getters/setters ommitted
</programlisting>

      <para/>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-custom-object-construction">
      <title>Customized Object Construction</title>

      <para>The mapping subsystem allows the customization of the object
      construction by annotating a constructor with the
      <literal>@PersistenceConstructor</literal> annotation. The values to be
      used for the constructor parameters are resolved in the following
      way:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a parameter is annotated with the <code>@Value</code>
          annotation, the given expression is evaluated and the result is used
          as the parameter value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If the Java type has a property whose name matches the given
          field of the input document, then it's property information is used
          to select the appropriate constructor parameter to pass the input
          field value to. This works only if the parameter name information is
          present in the java .class files which can be achieved by compiling
          the source with debug information or using the new
          <literal>-parameters</literal> command-line switch for javac in Java
          8.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Otherwise an <classname>MappingException</classname> will be
          thrown indicating that the given constructor parameter could not be
          bound.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <programlisting language="java">class OrderItem {
  
  private @Id String id;
  private int quantity;
  private double unitPrice;

  OrderItem(String id, @Value("#root.qty ?: 0") int quantity, double unitPrice) {
    this.id = id;
    this.quantity = quantity;
    this.unitPrice = unitPrice;
  }

  // getters/setters ommitted
}

DBObject input = new BasicDBObject("id", "4711");
input.put("unitPrice", 2.5);
input.put("qty",5);
OrderItem item = converter.read(OrderItem.class, input);</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>The SpEL expression in the <literal>@Value</literal> annotation
        of the <literal>quantity</literal> parameter falls back to the value
        <literal>0</literal> if the given property path cannot be
        resolved.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Additional examples for using the
      <classname>@PersistenceConstructor</classname> annotation can be found
      in the <ulink
      url="https://github.com/spring-projects/spring-data-mongodb/blob/master/spring-data-mongodb/src/test/java/org/springframework/data/mongodb/core/convert/MappingMongoConverterUnitTests.java">MappingMongoConverterUnitTests</ulink>
      test suite.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-usage-indexes.compound-index">
      <title>Compound Indexes</title>

      <para>Compound indexes are also supported. They are defined at the class
      level, rather than on indidvidual properties.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Compound indexes are very important to improve the performance
        of queries that involve criteria on multiple fields</para>
      </note>

      <para>Here's an example that creates a compound index of
      <code>lastName</code> in ascending order and <code>age</code> in
      descending order: <example>
          <title>Example Compound Index Usage</title>

          <programlisting language="java">package com.mycompany.domain;

@Document
@CompoundIndexes({
    @CompoundIndex(name = "age_idx", def = "{'lastName': 1, 'age': -1}")
})
public class Person {

  @Id
  private ObjectId id;
  private Integer age;
  private String firstName;
  private String lastName;

}
          </programlisting>
        </example></para>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-usage-indexes.text-index">
      <title>Text Indexes</title>

      <note>
        <para>The text index feature is disabled by default for mongodb
        v.2.4.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Creating a text index allows to accumulate several fields into a
      searchable full text index. It is only possible to have one text index
      per collection so all fields marked with
      <interfacename>@TextIndexed</interfacename> are combined into this
      index. Properties can be weighted to influence document score for
      ranking results. The default language for the text index is english, to
      change the default language set
      <interfacename>@Document(language="spanish")</interfacename> to any
      language you want. Using a property called <literal>language</literal>
      or <interfacename>@Language</interfacename> allows to define a language
      override on a per document base.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example Text Index Usage</title>

        <programlisting language="java">@Document(language = "spanish")
class SomeEntity {
     
    @TextIndexed String foo;
 
    @Language String lang;
 
    Nested nested;
 
 
}
 
class Nested {
     
    @TextIndexed(weight=5) String bar;
 
    String roo;
}
    </programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-usage-references">
      <title>Using DBRefs</title>

      <para>The mapping framework doesn't have to store child objects embedded
      within the document. You can also store them separately and use a DBRef
      to refer to that document. When the object is loaded from MongoDB, those
      references will be eagerly resolved and you will get back a mapped
      object that looks the same as if it had been stored embedded within your
      master document.</para>

      <para>Here's an example of using a DBRef to refer to a specific document
      that exists independently of the object in which it is referenced (both
      classes are shown in-line for brevity's sake):</para>

      <example>
        <programlisting language="java">
@Document
public class Account {

  @Id
  private ObjectId id;
  private Float total;

}

@Document
public class Person {

  @Id
  private ObjectId id;
  @Indexed
  private Integer ssn;
  @DBRef
  private List&lt;Account&gt; accounts;

}
        </programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>There's no need to use something like <code>@OneToMany</code>
      because the mapping framework sees that you're wanting a one-to-many
      relationship because there is a List of objects. When the object is
      stored in MongoDB, there will be a list of DBRefs rather than the
      <code>Account</code> objects themselves. <important>
          <para>The mapping framework does not handle cascading saves. If you
          change an <code>Account</code> object that is referenced by a
          <code>Person</code> object, you must save the Account object
          separately. Calling <code>save</code> on the <code>Person</code>
          object will not automatically save the <code>Account</code> objects
          in the property <code>accounts</code>.</para>
        </important></para>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-usage-events">
      <title>Mapping Framework Events</title>

      <para>Events are fired throughout the lifecycle of the mapping process.
      This is described in the <link
      linkend="mongodb.mapping-usage.events">Lifecycle Events</link>
      section.</para>

      <para>Simply declaring these beans in your Spring ApplicationContext
      will cause them to be invoked whenever the event is dispatched.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mapping-explicit-converters">
      <title>Overriding Mapping with explicit Converters</title>

      <para>When storing and querying your objects it is convenient to have a
      <interfacename>MongoConverter</interfacename> instance handle the
      mapping of all Java types to DBObjects. However, sometimes you may want
      the <interfacename>MongoConverter</interfacename>'s do most of the work
      but allow you to selectivly handle the conversion for a particular type
      or to optimize performance.</para>

      <para>To selectivly handle the conversion yourself, register one or more
      one or more
      <classname>org.springframework.core.convert.converter.Converter</classname>
      instances with the MongoConverter.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Spring 3.0 introduced a core.convert package that provides a
        general type conversion system. This is described in detail in the
        Spring reference documentation section entitled <ulink
        url="http://docs.spring.io/spring/docs/3.2.x/spring-framework-reference/html/validation.html#core-convert">Spring
        3 Type Conversion</ulink>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>The method <methodname>customConversions</methodname> in
      <classname>AbstractMongoConfiguration</classname> can be used to
      configure Converters. The examples <link
      linkend="mapping-configuration">here</link> at the begining of this
      chapter show how to perform the configuration using Java and XML.</para>

      <para>Below is an example of a Spring Converter implementation that
      converts from a DBObject to a Person POJO.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">@ReadingConverter
 public class PersonReadConverter implements Converter&lt;DBObject, Person&gt; {

  public Person convert(DBObject source) {
    Person p = new Person((ObjectId) source.get("_id"), (String) source.get("name"));
    p.setAge((Integer) source.get("age"));
    return p;
  }

}</programlisting>

      <para>Here is an example that converts from a Person to a
      DBObject.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">@WritingConverter
public class PersonWriteConverter implements Converter&lt;Person, DBObject&gt; {

  public DBObject convert(Person source) {
    DBObject dbo = new BasicDBObject();
    dbo.put("_id", source.getId());
    dbo.put("name", source.getFirstName());
    dbo.put("age", source.getAge());
    return dbo;
  }

}</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
