<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="get-started">
  <title>Additional Help Resources</title>

  <para>Learning a new framework is not always straight forward. In this
  section, we (the Spring Data team) tried to provide, what we think is, an
  easy to follow guide for starting with Spring Data Document module. However,
  if you encounter issues or you are just looking for an advice, feel free to
  use one of the links below:</para>

  <section id="get-started:help">
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>There are a few support options available:</para>

    <section id="get-started:help:community">
      <title>Community Forum</title>

      <para>The Spring Data <ulink
      url="http://forum.springframework.org/forumdisplay.php?f=80">forum
      </ulink> is a message board for all Spring Data (not just Document)
      users to share information and help each other. Note that registration
      is needed <emphasis>only</emphasis> for posting.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="get-started:help:professional">
      <title>Professional Support</title>

      <para>Professional, from-the-source support, with guaranteed response
      time, is available from <ulink
      url="http://www.springsource.com">SpringSource</ulink>, the company
      behind Spring Data and Spring.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="get-started:up-to-date">
    <title>Following Development</title>

    <para>For information on the Spring Data Mongo source code repository,
    nightly builds and snapshot artifacts please see the <ulink
    url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data/mongodb">Spring Data Mongo
    homepage</ulink>.</para>

    <para>You can help make Spring Data best serve the needs of the Spring
    community by interacting with developers through the Spring Community
    <ulink url="http://forum.springsource.org">forums</ulink>. To follow
    developer activity look for the mailing list information on the Spring
    Data Mongo homepage.</para>

    <para>If you encounter a bug or want to suggest an improvement, please
    create a ticket on the Spring Data issue <ulink
    url="https://jira.springframework.org/browse/DATAKV">tracker</ulink>.</para>

    <para>To stay up to date with the latest news and announcements in the
    Spring eco system, subscribe to the Spring Community <ulink
    url="http://www.springframework.org/">Portal</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Lastly, you can follow the SpringSource Data <ulink
    url="http://blog.springsource.com/category/data-access/">blog </ulink>or
    the project team on Twitter (<ulink
    url="http://twitter.com/SpringData">SpringData</ulink>)</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
